<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Sharavanan Balasundaravel</title>
  <subtitle>I build software, make music and occasionally write about stuff that interests me.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://sharavananpa.dev/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://sharavananpa.dev/" />
  <updated>2024-08-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://sharavananpa.dev/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Sharavanan Balasundaravel</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Where do I see myself in 2028?</title>
    <link href="https://sharavananpa.dev/writings/project-2028/" />
    <updated>2024-08-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://sharavananpa.dev/writings/project-2028/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;To be born in the year &amp;quot;2000&amp;quot; is a great convenience. It is easier to calculate your age — you don&#39;t have to add or subtract anything from the current year and the year just equals your age.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I thought that starting this year, and every four years from now, I’d honestly answer one of the most platitudinous questions ever asked in a job interview. I will try to break down this question further and cover the entire context. This is almost like a &lt;em&gt;letter to my future self&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main reasons to do this are,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;One... I feel this will point me in a direction in life with better precision.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Two... It will be cool to see how my goals and values change over time.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If I live till 2100, I&#39;ll have to do this exercise around 20 times. I think that is a fair amount of commitment. This is a time better spent than scrolling through social media at least!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-am-i-up-to-right-now&quot;&gt;What am I up to right now?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am in a transitional phase. Things are uncertain, and I can&#39;t even say what I&#39;ll be doing after the next six months. But I do have a direction. Two directions, actually — one is music and the other is computer science. I&#39;m gonna keep grinding for the next five to six months. My whole existence right now revolves around practicing the piano, attending audio engineering lectures, and honing my problem-solving skills. I do get off the rails sometimes. I get burnt out and don&#39;t feel like doing anything for a while. But somehow, by doing this and that and keeping track in spreadsheets, I throw myself onto the track.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One thing I’ve realized is that it’s better to outsource your accountability. The mechanism and structure that we get in an academic setting can&#39;t be created by ourselves unless the motivation is really up there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I take my health into consideration these days. I try to eat good food. I&#39;m eating out most of the time, and it gets really expensive. That&#39;s something that bugs me, but I don&#39;t think I have a choice right now. Overall, I feel good that I can do what I want to do. Occasionally, I miss my family. Periodically, I overthink. But mostly, I am doing well!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-would-should-change-in-the-next-4-years&quot;&gt;What would/should change in the next 4 years?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;livelihood&quot;&gt;Livelihood&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I should be in a very stable position. I don&#39;t think I can make any dicey decisions when I&#39;m 28. I should have a stronghold in at least one of the two things I&#39;m up to. This would probably be in computer science because that&#39;s where the most opportunities are. And that won&#39;t happen magically when I turn 28. I&#39;ll have to work for it right from now (and I&#39;m doing it). This was one of the major reasons for me to quit my full-time job post-haste. If I hadn&#39;t done it, I don&#39;t think I could&#39;ve done it in 2028. I put a lot of thought and time into filtering down my life into two things, and they still feel overwhelming. We can go as deep as we want into either of these fields. I feel like each of these demand its own lifetime, and here I am trying to do both with just one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;marriage&quot;&gt;Marriage&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think I’ll be married by then. I understand that my parents are very eager. I wouldn&#39;t say I&#39;m not eager, but I have a lot of other things to be enthusiastic about. What else do you expect from an ambitious workaholic? But I really do think it is better to get married early on if you&#39;re in India. As you age, the pool of prospective partners diminishes exponentially. This is obviously a societal thing but sorry to spoil it for you — we are a part of that society! It really doesn&#39;t help being frustrated over things that aren&#39;t in our control. I did all that when I was in my teens — believe me, it doesn&#39;t help at all. I&#39;m not saying that we can&#39;t change bigger things — of course we can. All I&#39;m saying is we can&#39;t fight everyone at the same time. We gotta choose our fights!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;music&quot;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;It might be very premature to comment on music and think of what I&#39;ll be doing with it in 4 years. But I&#39;ll try to condense some of my thoughts into words here. Before I came here to the conservatory, I kinda knew that the job market in this industry was bleak. I still came here because, one: I should not make assumptions and regret not doing it later, two: I had a little hope that I would be able to thrive here and even find a job that would take me up the ladder, and three: I knew I can always go back to being a software engineer. I was utterly confused about what to do because it wasn&#39;t a simple choice. I really feel I can do well in music, but we won&#39;t see the results until later. It will be too late and it will affect all other aspects and people around me. I can&#39;t be that selfish. The puddle of doubts cleared a bit when I spoke to my professor about it. I&#39;m glad I did that. It gave me a better perspective. It all boiled down to a simple question — What do I want out of music? I can be an Audio Engineer and work for other people, but I already have a better-paying alternative for that. If I&#39;m really honest, all I want from music is money and fame! And to achieve that, just being skilled is not enough. There is something more that is required. My professor calls it talent. Inside me, I really feel that I have got what it takes to become what I want. I wouldn&#39;t call it over-confidence. I am someone who tries to avoid negative evaluations at any cost. I am almost docile in that sense and would&#39;ve easily done everything that everyone wants from me. I totally despise being frowned upon. And, for me to do all the things that I&#39;ve done and to make all the choices that I&#39;ve made — this can&#39;t just be over-confidence is what I feel. Nobody would&#39;ve stopped me from making music if it was just a hobby but I don&#39;t want it to be &amp;quot;just a hobby&amp;quot;. I want to create music that people truly like and can connect with.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;family&quot;&gt;Family&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I always feel as though I’m the chosen one. That could partly be attributed to some personality disorder, but it&#39;s mostly because I&#39;m really lucky! It all starts right from when you&#39;re born and who you&#39;re born to. I got a good education only because my parents were able to afford it. I stumbled upon music only because we had a computer at home. We had computers at home only because my dad was a software consultant. And the list goes on. Although my parents are self-sufficient, I feel like I should give them a proper retirement before 2028. I think their only concern right now is whether I’m self-sufficient. I would like to be around them if situations permit it when I&#39;m 28, but it&#39;s highly unlikely. Times have changed and this isn&#39;t the &#39;80s anymore. I&#39;ll have to be at a place where things happen, and Coimbatore hasn&#39;t become that place yet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-i-look-at-the-larger-picture&quot;&gt;How do I look at the larger picture?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bigger goal is actually simple. After removing all the complexities associated with the smaller plans, the main goal is to earn a significant amount of money. The wealth I’m after will elevate those around me, both this generation and the next. I think money was one of the biggest factors that demanded me to take the longer route to do what I wanted to do. I genuinely don&#39;t want that to happen to the younger generation — my cousins, nephews and nieces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The way I see my life panning out is quite simple too. I&#39;ve split it into three phases. The first phase is to explore different things and figure out what I want to do in life. The second phase is to do that thing for decades. The third phase is when, after attaining a certain level of proficiency at what I do, I should give it back by being a mentor or a teacher.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first phase is almost over. I&#39;ve never felt this confident about what I want to do. The next step is to do them consistently and create some value out of them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, I just have to keep myself healthy throughout so that I don&#39;t die prematurely!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See y&#39;all in 2028...&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Pongal in Chennai</title>
    <link href="https://sharavananpa.dev/writings/pongal-in-chennai/" />
    <updated>2024-01-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://sharavananpa.dev/writings/pongal-in-chennai/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;An interesting thing happened this week!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got to stay in Chennai during this year’s Pongal. This was the first time I&#39;ve been outside Coimbatore during Pongal. I&#39;ve never seen Chennai like this before. My roommate and I went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tamilnadutourism.tn.gov.in/destinations/thiruvanmiyur-beach&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thiruvanmiyur beach&lt;/a&gt; in the morning and spent an hour or two there. The beach was nearly empty, the roads were vacant and the weather was top-notch. It was the complete opposite of how I’ve perceived Chennai so far.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After that, we headed back to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geethamveg.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;restaurant&lt;/a&gt; near our house. It was extremely helpful for people like me to have restaurants open during Pongal, but I do feel sorry for their employees. I hope they’re not exploited and are paid fairly. That said, they seemed pretty happy that day. They wished us well and even served us some Sakkarai Pongal — it was delicious.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Disinformation Peddling</title>
    <link href="https://sharavananpa.dev/writings/disinformation-peddling/" />
    <updated>2024-01-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://sharavananpa.dev/writings/disinformation-peddling/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am inherently a skeptic. Even if things are socially accepted, I don&#39;t usually conform to them. In fact, I very much like to break out from what&#39;s normal and try to be different (idk if that&#39;s for good or bad). I&#39;m somewhat of a contrarian.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was in school when social media became popular. From then till now, they just don&#39;t feel very real to me. On the other side, I hear a lot about how people fell in love by just connecting through social media. That is, as far as I am concerned, very real.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But, even for people like me who don&#39;t trust the internet that much, it&#39;s increasingly becoming difficult to know what&#39;s true and what&#39;s not. With the internet getting a lot more accessible, misinformation is spreading left, right and centre. I feel like it&#39;s really important to have a critical view of everything that we consume on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One thing that I try to do is to understand where the information is coming from. If it&#39;s from a person or an organisation, I explore a bit about what they do and what views they hold onto. You can easily spot a con man by just taking a look at their resumé. It usually will be very lean or they&#39;ll be trying to sell you something. These are the two main red flags. One reason it&#39;s very difficult to rule out someone as a con artist is because they usually encapsulate the lies within truths. On the surface, they may seem very logical but if you take them as it is, it&#39;s going to poison your system. All the godmen and self-proclaimed gurus I find on the internet seem to use this technique. Most of what they say is just common sense and you feel good about yourself when someone validates what you already know. But, right after that, you&#39;ll be bombarded with &lt;a href=&quot;https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Pseudoscience&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pseudo-scientific woos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From now on, I’ve decided to ignore these kinds of people rather than get frustrated, and just focus on the good stuff that’s there.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My email to Darbuka Siva</title>
    <link href="https://sharavananpa.dev/writings/my-email-to-darbuka-siva/" />
    <updated>2022-08-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://sharavananpa.dev/writings/my-email-to-darbuka-siva/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During the pandemic, at a time when I had high fever, a movie that I had been expecting for quite some time got released on an OTT platform. I watched it with all the discomfort of the fever (possibly caused by the COVID-19 virus).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I loved the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mudhal_Nee_Mudivum_Nee&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;film&lt;/a&gt;! The film revolves around a bunch of school kids studying in a catholic school (just like I did), and the main character is interested in music (just like me). The connection I felt with the movie was so strong that I had to find the director&#39;s (and the music composer&#39;s - for this film, Darbuka Siva was both) email ID from the internet and write him an email telling him how much I liked the film.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is how happiness works. He made me happy and I in turn wanted to make him happy. After I wrote that email, it was in my drafts for 7 to 8 months. I had a &amp;quot;no reply anxiety&amp;quot;. It is absurd to think that I was afraid to send an email to someone who doesn&#39;t know who I am and what I do and has no direct impact on my life whatsoever. Also, this was the time I was finally transitioning between college and work. I had my internship work on one hand and I had the project work on the other. It was too hectic and there was no time to think about anything else. After college was over, I didn&#39;t want to delay it anymore. I just felt like sending it. I added a note at the top with reasons for my delay and sent it without thinking too much.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;monospace-font smaller-font&quot;&gt;(The above text was written wayy later to provide context.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the email...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;left-border&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Tue, Aug 9, 2022 at 1:12 PM Sharavanan Balasundaravel &amp;lt;&lt;s&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:redacted@gmail.com&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;redacted@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/s&gt;&amp;gt; wrote:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: This mail was in my drafts folder for so long. I kinda wrote this after a week or so after the film&#39;s release. Now the effects of this film have definitely faded (I wish I had sent this earlier while it was hot). I was a little hesitant and didn&#39;t know if you&#39;ll read this or not. But now I&#39;ve changed my mind. There&#39;s no point in keeping this any longer. I&#39;m sending this right away!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi Siva na,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is Sharavanan from Coimbatore. I&#39;m a final year undergraduate student. I really hope you read this. I watched Mudhal Nee Mudivum Nee a while back and I couldn&#39;t stop thinking about it even after so many days (I watch a lot of films and rarely do they stay this long).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just 10 minutes into the film, I knew this film was gonna be at the top of my list. The relatability is so strong. I felt like watching myself when I saw Vinod (except for Rekha&#39;s part - I studied in a boys&#39; school :&#39;)). I remember downloading pirated softwares and making mediocre beats and sounds when I was in my 10th standard. This was the time when these new wave of music directors like Anirudh, Santhosh Narayanan and Hip-hop Tamizha were starting out. It was a light bulb moment for me when I came to know that I can make music using computers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I cannot remember a time when we didn&#39;t have a computer at home (my dad&#39;s a software developer btw). I&#39;ve had computers my whole life and didn&#39;t know that I could make music using it. Then I watched tutorials and courses on YouTube and made even more (okayish) music. My friends were kinda supportive (they were the only people who listen to my music so...) and this went on for 1 or 2 years after I was into college. I feel like I&#39;ve lost the spark in the process of getting my Engineering degree (but I&#39;ve not quit yet). I kinda started thinking like my peers (you know coding, placements and stuff) and sidelined music. I even thought of quitting (when I didn&#39;t even start - smh) music and start focusing on my software career until I saw MNMN. I generally do not ponder over my past but after watching your film I couldn&#39;t help it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d say I&#39;m an above average software engineer. I can even do better than that but I highly doubt if I can be the best (especially with a regret that I didn&#39;t even try to get into music). I also feel like this is a good time to step back and think about what I&#39;d want to do in life (now that college is soon to be over).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I really don&#39;t know if I&#39;m right for music. I&#39;m definitely not very good at music right now (this I know). But I won&#39;t know for sure until I&#39;ve tried it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll have to start again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t know if you&#39;ll read this but some acknowledgement would be nice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Again, thank you for making this film!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharavanan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I did get a reply after three days...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;left-border&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Fri, 12 Aug, 2022, 12:20 pm Darbuka Siva, &amp;lt;&lt;s&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:redacted@gmail.com&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;redacted@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/s&gt;&amp;gt; wrote:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi Sharavanan,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the mail. I&#39;m really happy to hear about how much of a connection you have with MNMN.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hope you get to do all the things you love doing. All the best for that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Darbuka Siva&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FIN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>